<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Substance of Sustainability - energy</title><link href="//sustainsubstance.org/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="//sustainsubstance.org/feeds/energy.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>//sustainsubstance.org/</id><updated>2024-04-30T08:26:38+02:00</updated><entry><title>On Energy, part 1: How much do we use?</title><link href="//sustainsubstance.org/energy-intro.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-02-12T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-04-15T11:44:47+02:00</updated><author><name>Levien van Zon</name></author><id>tag:sustainsubstance.org,2017-02-12:/energy-intro.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Levien van Zon&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Reading time: 5-10 minutes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We live in interesting times. Humanity has never had as much energy at its disposal as we have had over the last half century or so. Given this abundance, our complex societies have flourished, yet they have also become increasingly dependent on …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Levien van Zon&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Reading time: 5-10 minutes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We live in interesting times. Humanity has never had as much energy at its disposal as we have had over the last half century or so. Given this abundance, our complex societies have flourished, yet they have also become increasingly dependent on the availability of cheap energy sources. The last few decades however, things seem to be changing. Fossil energy is becoming increasingly expensive&lt;sup id="fnref:fossilprices"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fossilprices"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and the negative side-effects of burning large amounts of fossil fuels are becoming apparent. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The past years have been the warmest years on record&lt;sup id="fnref:warmestyears"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:warmestyears"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and the first effects of global warming on regional climates are starting to become apparent and are already causing problems for people all over the world. In an international effort to slow climate change, many countries signed the Paris climate treaty in 2016. Under the treaty, countries committed themselves to basically phasing out atmospheric emissions from fossil fuels by 2050. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While most industrialised countries are still very much dependent on fossil fuels, an increasing number of countries and companies are starting to see the transition away from fossil fuels as an economic opportunity. Especially China, although currently the largest greenhouse gas emitter, is positioning itself as the leading provider of alternative energy infrastructure.&lt;sup id="fnref:chinatransition"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:chinatransition"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Technological development and increasing investment in alternative energy have led to a sharp drop in the prices of wind and solar power. Meanwhile, anticipating the shift away from oil, most major car brands have announced plans to move away from combustion engines and focus exclusively on electric vehicles in the near future. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, we&amp;rsquo;re only at the start of a transition away from fossil energy, and serious challenges remain on our way. The United States, globally the second-biggest emitter of greenhouse gasses, currently has a national government bent on stretching and even increasing fossil fuel use for as long as possible. Perhaps more seriously, few people realise how much fossil energy we actually use. While scaling up alternative energy sources to this level is theoretically possible, it is certainly not going to be easy, especially not in the short term and not in all countries. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the first of two articles on energy use.&lt;sup id="fnref:numbers"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:numbers"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In this article, I shall look at how much energy we use and where it comes from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;A brief history of energy&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I already suggested in the introduction, we live in a rather unique period in history. Not only do we have more energy at our disposal than ever before, energy has also never been as cheap as it has been over the last century or so. Granted, especially oil prices have fluctuated quite a bit during this period, as you can see in the chart below. As recently as 2011, the price of crude oil was at an almost historic high. At $0.74 per litre, the oil price in 2011 was more than ten times that in 1970! But we easily forget that oil actually contains &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; of energy. A convenient measure of energy is the kilowatt-hour (kWh), which I will explain in a bit, but which you may recognise from your electricity bills. A litre of oil contains roughly 10 kWh of energy, so even the extremely high 2011 oil price translates to a mere 7 dollar-cents per kWh, which, in the grand scheme of things, is really not that much.&lt;sup id="fnref:energyprices"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:energyprices"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="//sustainsubstance.org/pages/energy-prices.html"&gt;&lt;img alt="Crude oil price 1860-2015 in 2015 US dollars" src="//sustainsubstance.org/images/oilprice-1860-2015.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The global price of a litre of crude oil from 1860 to 2015. Historical prices are inflation-corrected and are expressed in 2015 US dollars, for fair comparison. Click on the image for &lt;a href="({static}/pages/energy-prices.md)"&gt;more information&lt;/a&gt;. Data source: &lt;a href="http://www.bp.com/statisticalreview"&gt;BP Statistical Review of World Energy, June 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fact is that &lt;em&gt;we all have become rather dependent on energy being so cheap&lt;/em&gt;, because we use an incredible amount of it, especially in industrialised countries. In many ways, this abundance of cheap energy is a good thing. Energy quite literally powers everything we do. Things like food production, transport, heating and cooling become a lot easier and cheaper with abundant energy, and modern communication wouldn&amp;rsquo;t even be possible without it. So what exactly is the problem? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take a look at the following graph, which shows how much energy we humans use per day, and where it comes from, from 1800 until the present day. (These are fairly rough estimates, expressed in terawatt-hours, a unit which I shall explain in a moment.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="//sustainsubstance.org/pages/energy-timeseries.html"&gt;&lt;img alt="global primary energy use since 1800" src="//sustainsubstance.org/images/energy-timeseries-total-per-day.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until the nineteenth century, people almost exclusively used biomass (stuff directly derived from plants or animals) as an energy source. Things like cooking, heating and lighting were done using wood, charcoal, peat, dung and whale-oil. Transport and agriculture were mostly powered by humans and animals such as horses, mules and cattle. Wind and water played an important role as well, in industry (windmills and watermills) and in long-distance transport (think sailing ships).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 1850 the Industrial Revolution was well on its way. The Industrial Revolution was as much about technical innovation as it was about social change and energy transition: Technological developments were intimately tied to the availability of cheap labour and the large-scale mining of fossil coal. But the use of coal was still mostly limited to cities, to industry and to steam locomotives and ships. In 1850, firewood was still and by far the most important energy source for humanity. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 1900, the use of coal had caught up to be more or less equal to the use of biomass. The half-century that followed saw a further increase in the use of coal for industry, heating and transport. It also saw the slow expansion of car use and the development of aeroplanes, both of which required oil as an energy source. The two world wars were an important driver for technological development and the expansion of fossil fuel mining.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the end of World War II, the energy provided by coal had doubled again, it now provided almost twice as much energy as biomass. Also, the large-scale use of natural gas and oil really started take off. A mere two decades later, by the 1970s, oil had become the most important energy source, closely followed by coal and gas. This just goes to show how quickly the energy landscape can change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since 1800, human energy use has increased roughly 28-fold, and 82% of our energy is now provided by fossil fuels. Of course this enormous increase in global energy use is in part due to the more than seven-fold increase in world population over the last two centuries. If we factor this out and look at the daily energy use &lt;em&gt;per human&lt;/em&gt;, the increase since 1800 has been somewhat more modest:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="//sustainsubstance.org/pages/energy-timeseries.html"&gt;&lt;img alt="average primary energy use per person since 1800" src="//sustainsubstance.org/images/energy-timeseries-per-person.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What you can see here is that the energy consumption &lt;em&gt;per person&lt;/em&gt; has gone up too: it almost doubled between 1800 and 1950, and has doubled again since then. However, we can see that most of this second doubling actually occurred during the 1960s and 70s. This period saw the rise of energy-intensive consumer culture, personal car ownership and comfortable housing for small families, at least in the Western world. In the 1980s and 90s, recession and increases in energy efficiency temporarily halted the growth of personal energy consumption. Energy efficiency is still increasing today, but unfortunately so is our absolute energy consumption in this age of digital gadgets, data centres, cheap air travel and increasingly heavy cars. This has led to a renewed increase in personal energy use over the last 15 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The kWh and other animals&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two centuries ago, in 1800, an average human was estimated to use just over 16 kWh per day. A century ago this had increased to just over 24 kWh per day. Today, the average person uses around 60 kWh per day. Before we continue, what is this kWh-thing exactly? The kiloWatt-hour (kW·h or kWh) is a measure of &lt;em&gt;energy&lt;/em&gt;. But how much energy exactly? Let&amp;rsquo;s look at a few examples (click on the image for more details).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="//sustainsubstance.org/pages/energy-kwh.html"&gt;&lt;img alt="The kilowatt-hour explained" src="//sustainsubstance.org/images/energy-kwh-explained.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, a kilowatt-hour (kWh) is sufficient energy to boil a bucket of water, to drive a bit over 1 kilometre by car, to power a laptop for a few days or to power a smartphone for a few months. As for the terawatt-hour (TWh) I mentioned earlier, 1 TWh is 1 billion kWh. So we humans currently use over 430 billion kWh of energy &lt;em&gt;per day&lt;/em&gt;. That&amp;rsquo;s a very large number, and a very large amount of energy. Then again, there are over 7 billion of us on this planet, so we are a lot of people. This is why I will mostly talk about average energy use per person, in kWh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mentioned this figure of 60 kWh per person per day, but actually that&amp;rsquo;s a bit misleading. This is the &lt;em&gt;average&lt;/em&gt; energy use of a human being, but very few people are average human beings. In fact, most humans worldwide use less energy than average. But if you&amp;rsquo;re reading this, chances are that you&amp;rsquo;re not one of them, and that you in fact use quite a bit more energy than average. This is what I shall discuss in the &lt;a href="//sustainsubstance.org/energy-regionaluse.html"&gt;next article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interested in reading more articles like this? Subscribe to my &lt;a href="https://lvzon.substack.com/"&gt;Substack&lt;/a&gt;, or follow me on &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/sustainsubstance"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://bsky.app/profile/lvzon.bsky.social"&gt;Bluesky&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/levienvanzon"&gt;Twitter/X&lt;/a&gt;. You can also subscribe to our &lt;a href="/feeds/all.atom.xml"&gt;Atom-feed&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Footnotes:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:warmestyears"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The past years have been the warmest years on record&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;br&gt;
Based on the NOAA dataset of annually-averaged global combined land and ocean temperatures, the top-4 warmest years since 1880 are: 1. 2017, 2. 2016, 3. 2015, 4. 2014. While this can be partially explained by a strong El Niño, to date, all 17 years of the 21&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; century rank among the eighteen warmest on record (the other one is 1998, which is currently the ninth warmest). The six warmest years in a 138-year temperature record have all occurred since 2010. Even if you account for some uncertainty, methodological problems and natural variation, this is still a rather worrying trend.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:warmestyears" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:fossilprices"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fossil energy is becoming increasingly expensive&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br&gt;
Some may object to this statement and point out the current low cost of fossil energy sources, and the decreasing costs of bringing the fairly abundant supplies of US shale gas and oil to market. However, if we take a longer-term view, it is very unlikely that fossil fuel costs will ever return to anywhere near the low level we saw in the 1960s. Increasing public pressure for higher carbon taxes and decreasing willingness to invest in long-term fossil fuel development will probably also drive up fossil energy prices in coming decades. For more information on past energy prices, see &lt;a href="//sustainsubstance.org/pages/energy-prices.html"&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:fossilprices" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:chinatransition"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;China, although currently the largest greenhouse gas emitter, is positioning itself as the leading provider of alternative energy infrastructure.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br&gt;
China is planning to invest billions in industries that can produce solar panels, windmills and long-distance energy transportation networks.
http://www.reuters.com/article/us-china-solar-idUSKBN15J0G7
China&amp;rsquo;s installed photovoltaic (PV) capacity more than doubled last year, turning the country into the world&amp;rsquo;s biggest producer of solar energy by capacity, the National Energy Administration (NEA) said on Saturday.
Installed PV capacity rose to 77.42 gigawatts at the end of 2016, with the addition of 34.54 gigawatts over the course of the year, data from the energy agency showed. 
Solar plants generated 66.2 billion kilowatt-hours of power last year, accounting for 1 percent of China&amp;rsquo;s total power generation, the NEA said.
The country aims to boost the mix of non-fossil fuel generated power to 20 percent by 2030 from 11 percent today.
China plans to plough 2.5 trillion yuan ($364 billion) into renewable power generation by 2020.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:chinatransition" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:numbers"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This gradually evolved into an article series, in which I try to shed some light on our current use of energy, and on the possible shape of the energy transition ahead.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br&gt;
My examination will necessarily be somewhat technical at times, as energy is a complex and technical subject. However, you can safely skip technical sections, as I will try to recap important points every now and then. There will also be numbers. I will try to explain without numbers where I can, but the numbers are actually crucial. The energy problem, as we shall see, is mainly a problem of scale, and scale is determined by numbers. Specifically, big numbers.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:numbers" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:energyprices"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A litre of oil contains roughly 10 kWh of energy, so even the extremely high 2011 oil price translates to a mere 7 dollar-cents per kWh, which, in the grand scheme of things, is really not that much.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br&gt;
The effective price per kWh of &lt;em&gt;usable&lt;/em&gt; energy will of course be higher, as converting one form of energy to another always implies losses. The 10 kWh of energy that is in a litre of oil can only be fully extracted in the form of heat. If you take the energy in oil or coal or natural gas and convert it into electricity, you&amp;rsquo;ll lose at least a quarter to a third of the energy in the conversion process, often even more. Still, in many countries electricity is also relatively cheap. In the US the &lt;a href="http://www.eia.gov/electricity/data/browser/#/topic/7?agg=0,1&amp;amp;geo=vvvvvvvvvvvvo&amp;amp;endsec=vg&amp;amp;freq=A&amp;amp;start=2001&amp;amp;end=2015&amp;amp;ctype=linechart&amp;amp;ltype=pin&amp;amp;rtype=s&amp;amp;pin=&amp;amp;rse=0&amp;amp;maptype=0"&gt;average electricity price&lt;/a&gt; is only slightly over 10 dollar cents per kWh (a bit more for residential use). While oil was expensive in 2011, &lt;a href="https://www.ovoenergy.com/guides/energy-guides/average-electricity-prices-kwh.html"&gt;this comparison of 2011 electricity prices&lt;/a&gt; shows that the relative cost of electricity (adjusted for purchasing power) was below 12 dollar cents per kWh in Canada, China and the US. Electricity is generally generated from coal and natural gas, the price of which is linked to oil prices but only loosely. Electricity prices are therefore typically not a very good reflection of oil prices, or even of fossil fuel prices. Moreover, readers who have followed &lt;a href="http://www.pv-magazine.com/news/details/beitrag/abu-dhabi--three-world-record-bids-entered-for-sweihan-solar-project_100026191"&gt;recent developments in solar energy costs&lt;/a&gt; will have noticed that the expected cost for solar-generated electricity has recently dropped below 3 dollar cents per kWh for some projects in the Middle East. While such low costs will certainly not be realistic for projects in less optimal locations, it certainly is a promising development that solar energy now &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be cheaper than electricity from coal, at least in certain cases and areas.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:energyprices" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="energy"></category><category term="energy"></category></entry><entry><title>On Energy, part 2: We are not average</title><link href="//sustainsubstance.org/energy-regionaluse.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-02-12T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-04-30T08:26:38+02:00</updated><author><name>Levien van Zon</name></author><id>tag:sustainsubstance.org,2017-02-12:/energy-regionaluse.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Levien van Zon&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Reading time: 10 minutes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the second of two articles in which I try to shed some light on our current use of energy. In the &lt;a href="//sustainsubstance.org/energy-intro.html"&gt;previous article&lt;/a&gt; I introduce the kilowatt-hour (kWh), and looked at how much energy we use on average. We observed …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Levien van Zon&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Reading time: 10 minutes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the second of two articles in which I try to shed some light on our current use of energy. In the &lt;a href="//sustainsubstance.org/energy-intro.html"&gt;previous article&lt;/a&gt; I introduce the kilowatt-hour (kWh), and looked at how much energy we use on average. We observed that, globally, around 82% of our energy is derived from fossil fuels. In this article I shall look at the large differences between regions and countries, and at the dismal state of renewable energy in industrialised nations so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the previous article I showed that we use around 60 kWh of energy per person per day, but actually this figure is a bit misleading. This is the &lt;em&gt;average&lt;/em&gt; energy use of a human being, but very few people are average human beings. In fact, most humans use less energy than average. But if you&amp;rsquo;re reading this, chances are that you don&amp;rsquo;t belong to this group. In fact, you probably use quite a bit more energy than average.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://eoimages.gsfc.nasa.gov/images/imagerecords/55000/55167/earth_lights_lrg.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="The Earth as seen by night in 1995 (source: NASA)" src="//sustainsubstance.org/images/nasa-earth-lights-1995.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On this satellite image compilation you can see that some parts of the planet use much more electricity than other parts, at least for lighting roads and buildings at night. Source: &lt;a href="https://visibleearth.nasa.gov/view.php?id=55167"&gt;NASA&lt;/a&gt;, 1995.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;You are not average&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see in this figure, countries and regions vary quite a lot in how much energy they use per person:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="//sustainsubstance.org/images/energy-tpes-iea-2014-kwh-person-day.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="Energy use per person per day for different countries" src="//sustainsubstance.org/images/energy-tpes-iea-2014-kwh-person-day.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The red bar in this figure is the average worldwide energy use. Most countries above it are either relatively wealthy, or they have a lot of industry or oil reserves. Most countries below it are lower-income countries. And most people live in low-income countries. In fact, three quarters of humanity lives in Asia (around 51.7%), Africa (15.5%) and Latin America (8.6%). Asians use 40 kWh/person/day, but if you leave out China this average drops to 22, and in a country like Bangladesh it&amp;rsquo;s only 7 kWh. Africans use 21 kWh/person/day, but someone in Central Africa uses only 8.5, and in some countries it&amp;rsquo;s even below 5 kWh/person/day. And most of the energy used in Africa is actually firewood for cooking. It seems that there is a strong relationship between &amp;ldquo;development&amp;rdquo; and energy use&lt;sup id="fnref:HDI"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:HDI"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. A minority of humans use most of the world&amp;rsquo;s energy supply, while most people still use as much energy (or less) as humans did a century ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be fair, the level of &amp;ldquo;human development&amp;rdquo; certainly isn&amp;rsquo;t the only factor in energy use. Climate and geography play an important role in our need for energy. The countries where energy use per person is highest all have cold winters and/or warm summers and tend to have a relatively low population density. Such countries may need more energy for heating in winter or cooling in summer, and for transportation year-round. And then there&amp;rsquo;s industry, which also tends to require a lot of energy. This is especially important for a country such as China, which not only houses a fifth of the world&amp;rsquo;s population but also most of its manufacturing industry.&lt;sup id="fnref:china"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:china"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Many manufacturing processes require high temperatures, which in turn require a lot of energy. The industrial products are generally meant for export, which means that the average Chinese person actually uses a lot less energy than shown in the figure above, while the average consumer in a Western country may use quite a bit more. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if we don&amp;rsquo;t count the &amp;ldquo;indirect&amp;rdquo; energy use from consumption, the differences in energy use between countries are sometimes enormous. For instance, the United States are home to a mere 4.4% of the world&amp;rsquo;s population, less than Bangladesh and Pakistan combined. But the US uses over 16% of the world energy supply, while Bangladesh and Pakistan together use only 0.9%. The average North American uses over thirty times as much energy as the average Bangladeshi. It&amp;rsquo;s obvious that energy consumption will be higher in countries with lots of public infrastructure, where most people have their own car and house, and where most building have heating or air-conditioning, compared to countries where people are struggling to get by. And if living conditions are to improve in a country like Bangladesh, energy consumption needs to &lt;em&gt;increase&lt;/em&gt; there, rather than decrease. It would obviously be rather unfair to state that such countries should not be allowed to increase their standard of living. But it would also be unrealistic to expect richer countries to voluntarily &lt;em&gt;decrease&lt;/em&gt; their standard of living. As we shall see in later articles, the richer countries can actually decrease their energy use quite a lot without sacrificing living standards. But the energy problem is not only about &lt;em&gt;how much&lt;/em&gt; we use, it is also about &lt;em&gt;where the energy comes from&lt;/em&gt;. And in this respect there are significant differences between countries as well:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="//sustainsubstance.org/images/energy-tpes-iea-2014-energy-sources.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="Energy use per person per day by source, for different countries" src="//sustainsubstance.org/images/energy-tpes-iea-2014-energy-sources.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s start with some similarities: Most countries shown here need quite a bit of oil, up to 9 litres per person per day, which comes down to between 10 and 86 kWh of oil-derived energy per day for each person. This oil is used mostly for transport. On top of oil, most countries use a fair amount of coal, natural gas or nuclear energy, or a combination of these, to generate heat and electricity. Only very few countries use significant amounts of renewable energy. Iceland clearly stands out, being a volcanic island with a cold climate, a tiny population and abundant supplies of geothermal energy. A few other countries in this figure also stand out when it comes to renewable energy. Norway gets around a third of its energy from hydro power, and Canada, Switzerland, Austria, Sweden and New Zealand manage a little over 10%. New Zealand also gets &lt;a href="http://www.mbie.govt.nz/info-services/sectors-industries/energy/energy-data-modelling/statistics/renewables"&gt;around 20%&lt;/a&gt; of its energy from geothermal sources. 
But actually most renewable energy isn&amp;rsquo;t geothermal or hydro-power, and it certainly doesn&amp;rsquo;t come from solar or wind power.
Even in most advanced industrial countries, it turns out that the biggest &amp;ldquo;green&amp;rdquo; energy source is still firewood! This is followed in second place by waste material (including household waste and agricultural waste). In other words, most &amp;ldquo;renewable energy&amp;rdquo; comes from burning biomass and waste, much as it did 200 years ago. A country such as Finland has little hydro power and almost no windmills or solar panels, but it does have trees, lots of trees. As for some other countries:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="display: block; margin: 30px 0; width: 80vw; margin-left: 50%; -webkit-transform: translateX(-50%); -moz-transform: translateX(-50%); -ms-transform: translateX(-50%); -o-transform: translateX(-50%); transform: translateX(-50%);"&gt;
&lt;a href="//sustainsubstance.org/images/energy-country-consumption-countries-2013.png"&gt;
&lt;img src="//sustainsubstance.org/images/energy-country-consumption-countries-2013.png" /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it can certainly be sensible to generate some energy from waste and plant material, there&amp;rsquo;s no way we can run our current high-energy societies entirely on firewood. There simply aren&amp;rsquo;t enough trees in the world to do that. We need sustainable energy sources that are more scalable. Let&amp;rsquo;s therefore ignore the energy generated from biomass and waste for a moment. If we do that, things actually look pretty dismal when it comes to renewable energy. Worldwide, a little over 1% of energy comes from &amp;ldquo;other&amp;rdquo; renewable sources, including wind, solar and geothermal power. PV solar panels currently provide a little over 0.1% of global energy, which comes down to about around 0.04 kWh per person per day. A teaspoon of gasoline actually contains more energy than that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My home country of The Netherlands does only slightly better than the world average, it derives 0.7% of its energy from renewable sources outside of biomass and waste. In the UK this is 1.5%. Even Germany, generally considered to be a front-runner, only gets 3% of its energy from wind, solar and hydro power, which incidentally is the same percentage as France.&lt;sup id="fnref:renewablestats"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:renewablestats"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Spain and Portugal on the other hand, currently the poorest nations in Western Europe, do relatively well. Profiting from its relatively sunny climate, Spain is actually the European leader in solar energy at almost 2 kWh per person per day (2.4% of the country&amp;rsquo;s energy consumption). That&amp;rsquo;s still a small percentage, but when we consider other renewable sources, Spain currently gets 9% of its energy from wind, hydro power, thermal solar power and PV solar power. Portugal even manages a little over 10%. Granted, European countries with higher mountains and more water still tend to do a little better (Norway, Sweden and the Alpine countries)&lt;sup id="fnref:easterneurope"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:easterneurope"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, mainly because they have more hydro-power. Still, it&amp;rsquo;s interesting and hopeful to see that Portugal, Spain and even Greece (with 5.8%) are outperforming countries like Germany and Denmark, at least in generating their energy from sustainable sources outside of biomass and waste. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can clearly see that we have a long way to go if we want to switch all countries to a renewable energy supply. Even if we do count biomass and waste, the percentages of renewable energy are very small compared to the amount of fossil fuels we use. Let&amp;rsquo;s take The Netherlands as an example. The Netherlands is a tiny country with some 17 million people. But it actually uses more oil than &lt;em&gt;nearly all of the of the 40+ countries in sub-Saharan Africa taken together&lt;/em&gt; (if we exclude South Africa and Nigeria). And in fact, the wealth and the economy of The Netherlands depend very much on this. We currently need large amounts of oil to power the millions of cars, vans, trucks, tractors and boats that transport our people and goods and work our land. And then there&amp;rsquo;s all the coal and gas we use to heat our homes, offices and greenhouses, and to generate our electricity. Even a relatively small and wealthy country like The Netherlands would be hard-pressed to find sufficient alternative power sources to generate the more than 140 kWh per person per day it currently gets from fossil fuels.&lt;sup id="fnref:primaryvsfinal"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:primaryvsfinal"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; And these figures don&amp;rsquo;t even include the energy use of international air traffic and shipping. This large-scale use of fossil fuels is the biggest reason why an average Dutch person &lt;a href="//sustainsubstance.org/co2footprint.html"&gt;emits over 46 kg CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-eq.&lt;/a&gt; of greenhouse gasses per day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;So why is energy a problem?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fossil energy is a problem for at least two important reasons. First of all the supply of fossil fuels is not infinite. In fact, we haven&amp;rsquo;t discovered any major new conventional oil fields since the 1960s, and oil and gas are increasingly mined from old reservoirs and non-traditional sources such as oil shale and tar sands. We&amp;rsquo;re basically getting better at pulling fuel out of the ground, as a result of technical improvement. We can keep on doing this for at least a few decades, but it does come at a cost: The energy needed to get fossil fuels out of the ground is increasing, in some cases quite rapidly. For oil and gas it has more than doubled in the last 15-20 years. This is reflected in a measure called the energy return on energy investment (EROI or EROEI). The EROI tells us how much energy we get back for the energy we invest. It was as high as 33:1 for conventional oil and gas back in 1999, which means that for each kWh that we invested in looking for oil, pumping it out of the ground, and refining and transporting it, we ended up with a useful energy surplus of 33 kWh. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to sustain a complex society we actually need a fairly high return on energy investment. The reason for this is that you need a significant energy surplus to transport things, to feed everyone who doesn&amp;rsquo;t farm, to produce equipment, to do research, to build and maintain houses, offices, hospitals, schools, factories, stores, roads, power lines, gas pipes, computer networks and all the other infrastructure we&amp;rsquo;ve come to depend on in modern society. It has been estimated that the minimum EROI needed for the basic functioning of an industrial society is around 5:1. And that&amp;rsquo;s really a minimum, if you want to sustain more complex public infrastructure such as education and healthcare, you probably need at least 10:1 or 11:1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fossil fuels contain a lot of energy, so as long as you can get them out of the ground with ease, they yield a high return on energy investment. The problem is however that the average global EROI for oil and gas is going down. While it was around 33:1 in 1999, it had dropped to around 18:1 in 2005, and it is still declining. For US shale gas the EROI was estimated at 12:1 a few years ago. It probably went up a little in recent years, as low oil and gas prices forced efficiency improvements, but sooner or later it will decrease again as initial &amp;ldquo;sweet spots&amp;rdquo; are depleted. An EROI of 12:1 is already close to the minimum, and things get significantly worse when we make electricity from fossil fuels. The problem is again efficiency: we generally lose more than half our energy in conversion and transport. Electricity generated from conventional gas actually has an EROI around 7:1, and electricity from shale gas is probably around 5:1.&lt;sup id="fnref:eroisources"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:eroisources"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The falling global EROI for fossil fuels means that if we stick with current energy sources and if we do not decrease the current level of energy use, it may become a real challenge to keep our industrial societies running within a few decades. The effects of falling EROI will probably be noticeable well before that, as economic growth is coupled to energy surplus. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So our high energy needs are a problem, especially in combination with decreasing energy returns and a growing world population. But there&amp;rsquo;s perhaps a more pressing problem with our current energy situation: Every year, human activities release around 40 billion tonnes of greenhouse gasses (CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-equivalent) into the atmosphere. An estimated 69% of these emissions are the result of burning fossil fuels. We know with certainty that these emissions have a warming effect on the Earth&amp;rsquo;s climate. Apart from sea-level rise, we&amp;rsquo;re not entirely sure what the exact effects of climate change will be in the longer term, as I discussed in an &lt;a href="/co2.html"&gt;earlier article&lt;/a&gt;. This in itself is a problem. Models suggest some fairly nasty possible scenarios, including significant disruption of agriculture and biodiversity in large regions. In fact, it seems that this is already happening to some extent. Prolonged drought is causing structural water shortages in some regions (e.g. South Africa), while heavy rainfall is causing problems with flooding and erosion in other parts of the globe. To avoid serious climate disruption, we probably need to keep the warming of the global climate below 2 degrees Celsius. And to do this, we&amp;rsquo;d probably need to keep the total amount of human greenhouse gasses emitted after 2011 below 1 billion tonnes. At current rates of emission, this &amp;ldquo;carbon budget&amp;rdquo; will be used up in 2036.&lt;sup id="fnref:carbonbudgets"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:carbonbudgets"&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, if we manage to reduce our emissions, we may be able to stretch this budget a little longer. On the other hand, recent observations suggest that climate warming is actually proceeding faster than predicted by the IPCC models (which were used to estimate the carbon budgets). If this is indeed the case, we may have only a decade or two left to basically reduce human greenhouse gas emissions to zero. Given our enormous dependence on fossil energy, this is going to be an extremely difficult undertaking. It would probably require a dramatic increase in the energy efficiency of just about every human activity, as well as large-scale carbon capture, reversing deforestation, decreasing consumption, scaling up wind and especially solar energy more than a hundred-fold over existing levels, and building a completely new infrastructure for global energy transport and storage. And this all has to happen in a very short period of time, a few decades at most. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the Paris climate treaty, most governments have announced more or less ambitious goals to reduce fossil fuel use and scale up alternative energy sources. But it&amp;rsquo;s going require hard work and significant investment to meet those goals. Given the extremely high energy requirements of industrialised societies, just putting a few solar panels on a roof somewhere isn&amp;rsquo;t going to be enough to solve our energy and climate problems (by far, as I will discuss in a later article).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In its &lt;a href="https://www.iea.org/reports/world-energy-outlook-2017"&gt;World Energy Outlook 2017&lt;/a&gt;, the International Energy Agency (IEA) describes three possible scenarios for what the world energy system will look like in 2025 and 2040. Their most conservative &amp;ldquo;Current Policies&amp;rdquo; scenario takes into account only existing legislation for energy transition. This would lead to nearly a three-fold increase in solar and wind energy by 2040. This may sound impressive, until you realise that it would &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; lead to a significant growth in fossil fuel consumption.&lt;sup id="fnref:WEO2017"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:WEO2017"&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The use of fossil energy would grow by 36% and would still provide 79% of all energy in 2040 under current policies. Wind and solar would only provide a little over 4%. Unsurprisingly, greenhouse gas emissions would increase by 33% relative to today. The more optimistic &amp;ldquo;Sustainable Development&amp;rdquo; scenario analyses what policies would be needed to hit the targets of the Kyoto agreement. It would require a significant reduction in the use of coal by 2040, as well as a reduction in oil use, a slight &lt;em&gt;increase&lt;/em&gt; in the use of natural gas and almost a doubling in nuclear energy and hydro-power. Wind and solar would have to grow almost ten-fold, although they would still &amp;ldquo;only&amp;rdquo; provide around 14% of total energy in 2040, compared to 61% for fossil fuels. Greenhouse gas emissions would be around 43% lower than they are today, although this would require significant effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is actually rather risky to pretend that we can easily switch to renewable energy by just installing a few windmills and solar panels. It allows governments and corporations to get away with superficial and cosmetic measures, rather than making difficult, structural changes. Energy transition is not easy. New inexpensive large-scale energy sources will not magically materialise from research and innovation, at least not within the coming one or two decades. Energy transition will require blood, sweat, tears and a lot of investment, from everybody, from governments to companies and public institutions, and from researchers to house-owners. It&amp;rsquo;s time we started taking this more seriously, it&amp;rsquo;s time we really got to work and it&amp;rsquo;s time we all knew our numbers so we can actually be critical citizens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Recap: What have we learned so far?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We use &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; of energy, especially in industrialised countries that are located far from the equator. Currently, over 80% of this energy is derived from fossil fuels. The rest is largely derived from burning firewood and waste materials. The widespread use of fossil fuels is actually a fairly recent development, it was established mostly in the 1960s and 1970s. Energy use in Western, industrialised countries is much higher than elsewhere in the world. With a few exceptions (mostly countries with a lot of hydro-power), renewable energy sources outside waste and biomass provide only a &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; small fraction of the energy used in industrialised countries, sometimes a few percent but more generally less than one percent. Especially with regard to wind and solar energy there is certainly &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; of room for improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we&amp;rsquo;re not out of fossil fuels yet, the effective energy we get from especially oil and gas is declining, because most of the &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo; fossil fuels have already been mined and burnt. More importantly, if we want to avoid serious climate change, we may not be able to burn much of the fossil fuel reserves that we do have left. We would have to find other large-scale energy sources, and fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interested in reading more articles like this? Subscribe to my &lt;a href="https://lvzon.substack.com/"&gt;Substack&lt;/a&gt;, or follow me on &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/sustainsubstance"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://bsky.app/profile/lvzon.bsky.social"&gt;Bluesky&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/levienvanzon"&gt;Twitter/X&lt;/a&gt;. You can also subscribe to our &lt;a href="/feeds/all.atom.xml"&gt;Atom-feed&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Footnotes:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:HDI"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It seems that there is a strong relationship between &amp;ldquo;development&amp;rdquo; and energy use.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br&gt;
There seems to be a reasonable correlation between a country&amp;rsquo;s energy use and its &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_countries_by_Human_Development_Index"&gt;Human Development Index&lt;/a&gt;. 
The countries with the lowest energy use all score &amp;ldquo;low human development&amp;rdquo; (e.g. Niger, Eritrea, Senegal, South Sudan, Nepal) or at most &amp;ldquo;medium&amp;rdquo; development (e.g. Bangladesh). South Sudan is only a state since 2011, has been in civil war since 2013, and has ranked in the top-2 of the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fragile_States_Index"&gt;Fragile States Index&lt;/a&gt; for the last three years.
The countries with above-average energy use nearly all rank as &amp;ldquo;very high human development&amp;rdquo; (e.g. Canada, the United States, Saudi Arabia, most European countries, South Korea, Australia, Singapore, New Zealand, Japan, Israel) or &amp;ldquo;high&amp;rdquo; development (e.g. Russia, Iran, Bulgaria, Ukraine, China, Venezuela, Thailand), with only few exceptions (e.g. South Africa).&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:HDI" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:china"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is especially important for a country such as China, which not only houses a fifth of the world&amp;rsquo;s population but also most of its manufacturing industry.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br&gt;
As people in the West often point out, China is the world&amp;rsquo;s biggest emitter of greenhouse gases, as well as the world&amp;rsquo;s biggest consumer of coal. This is true, but in fact most of this energy is used for making export products. And even if we would count everything as domestic energy use, the population of China is so big that it comes down to only around 72 kWh per person per day, just above world average but well below the energy use of European countries.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:china" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:easterneurope"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Granted, European countries with higher mountains and more water still tend to do a little better (Norway, Sweden and the Alpine countries)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br&gt;
And in fact, some Eastern European countries do better as well. For instance, 34.35% of the supply of Albania comes from renewable sources, including 25.32% from hydro power and 0.5% from solar. Of course it helps that Albania is relatively small and has high mountains. But it&amp;rsquo;s a sobering thought that even a country like Romania still outperforms The Netherlands when it comes to the precentage of energy it gets from wind (1.2%) and solar power (0.11%).&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:easterneurope" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:renewablestats"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My home country of The Netherlands does only slightly better than the world average, it derives 0.7% of its energy from renewable sources outside of biomass and waste. In the UK this is 1.5%. Even Germany, generally considered to be a front-runner, only gets 3% of its energy from wind, solar and hydro power, which incidentally is the same percentage as France.&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;br&gt;
Many information sources mix up &lt;em&gt;energy use&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;electricity use&lt;/em&gt;, and fail to mention the dominant role of biomass and waste. This is the source of a lot of misleading statistics on renewable energy use. For instance, the contribution of renewable energy to total primary energy use in Germany is &lt;a href="https://www.bmwi.de/Redaktion/EN/Artikel/Energy/monitoring-implementation-of-the-energy-reforms.html"&gt;around 15%&lt;/a&gt;, of which around 12% is provided by biomass and waste. However, on average around 32% of German &lt;em&gt;electricity use&lt;/em&gt; is provided by renewable sources, and on particularly windy and sunny days this is can actually be over 100%. This leads to misleading news headlines such as &amp;ldquo;Germany Just Got Almost All of Its Power From Renewable Energy&amp;rdquo; (&lt;a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2016-05-16/germany-just-got-almost-all-of-its-power-from-renewable-energy"&gt;Bloomberg, 2016&lt;/a&gt;). In fact, even when there is a renewable energy surplus, which only happens a few days per year, Germany still derives at least a third of its energy from oil on such days, as well as a significant portion from coal and gas for heating and industrial processes. Moreover, peak energy consumption occurs mostly in winter, while a surplus of renewable electricity only occurs in spring and summer. Most news articles on the &amp;ldquo;sustainable energy revolution&amp;rdquo; in Germany also fail to mention that, on average, Germany uses a lot more fossil fuels than countries such as France, Spain and Portugal, and even a bit more than &amp;ldquo;dirty&amp;rdquo; countries such as the United Kingdom, Italy or most of Eastern Europe. Now don&amp;rsquo;t get me wrong, the expansion of solar and wind energy in Germany is certainly an impressive feat and a good thing, but it shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be used to obscure the plain fact that Germany still runs mostly on fossil fuels.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:renewablestats" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:primaryvsfinal"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Even a relatively small and wealthy country like The Netherlands would be hard-pressed to find sufficient alternative power sources to generate the more than 140 kWh per person per day it currently gets from fossil fuels.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br&gt;
Note that this figure is the so-called &lt;em&gt;primary&lt;/em&gt; energy use, which means the total energy used, including the losses associated with mining, conversion and transportation of energy. The amount of energy that we effectively use if we don&amp;rsquo;t count all these losses is called the &lt;em&gt;final&lt;/em&gt; energy use, and this tends to be quite a bit lower. For The Netherlands, the final energy use is around 90 kWh per person per day. Renewable energy sources like wind and solar power generally have fewer losses associated with mining, conversion and transport, so we would actually require less primary energy to do the same activities with renewable energy than with fossil energy. However, the figures for primary and final energy use do not include the energy required for the manufacturing of imports, and also do not include the energy requirements of international traffic. Both are probably substantial, so that the full &amp;ldquo;final&amp;rdquo; energy use of a person in The Netherlands is probably several times higher than 90 kWh/person/day.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:primaryvsfinal" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:eroisources"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;An EROI of 12:1 is already close to the minimum [&amp;hellip;] Electricity generated from conventional gas actually has an EROI around 7:1, and electricity from shale gas is probably around 5:1.&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;br&gt;
The 7:1 EROI for electricity from natural gas is based on figures from &lt;a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/eroi-behind-numbers-energy-return-investment/#"&gt;Mason Inman (2013)&lt;/a&gt;. The 33:1 (1999) and 18:1 (2005) for oil and gas were based on &lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3390%2Fen20300490"&gt;Gagnon et al. (2009)&lt;/a&gt;. The 12:1 estimate for US shale gas is based on &lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3390/en7042207"&gt;Yaritani &amp;amp; Matsushima (2014)&lt;/a&gt;. The minimum EROI-numbers are based on an &lt;a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/eroi-charles-hall-will-fossil-fuels-maintain-economic-growth/"&gt;interview with Charles Hall&lt;/a&gt;, in which he states: &amp;ldquo;If you&amp;rsquo;ve got an EROI of 1.1:1, you can pump the oil out of the ground and look at it. At 1.2:1 you can refine it and look at it. At 1.3:1 you can move it to where you want and look at it. [&amp;hellip;] You need at least 3:1 to drive a truck. If you want to put grain in the truck, you need 5:1. To include the truck-driver, oil-worker, farmer and their families, you need 7:1. If you want education, you need 8:1 or 9:1. If you want healthcare, you need 10:1 or 11:1.&amp;rdquo;  &lt;br&gt;
Some sustainable energy sources have a high energy return on investment, such as hydro-energy (more than 40:1) and wind energy (over 20:1 and rising). Modern PV solar energy generators still have a fairly low EROI of around 6:1 (this can be higher or lower, depending on location). Also this figure is increasing, but unfortunately batteries and other forms of storage are expected to significantly degrade this EROI again in the near future. Electricity from coal has a fairly stable EROI around 18:1, but carbon capture and storage may decrease this by around a third. Nuclear electricity has a rather variable EROI, which on average is fairly low (around 5:1) due to the extremely high energy costs of mining uranium, building and maintaining nuclear power plants and storing nuclear waste.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:eroisources" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:carbonbudgets"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;At current rates of emission, this &amp;ldquo;carbon budget&amp;rdquo; will be used up in 2036.&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;br&gt;
The 2013 &lt;a href="https://www.ipcc.ch/site/assets/uploads/2018/02/WG1AR5_SPM_FINAL.pdf"&gt;IPCC AR5 WG1 Summary for Policy Makers&lt;/a&gt; states that &lt;em&gt;limiting the warming caused by anthropogenic CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-emissions alone with a probability of &amp;gt;66% to less than 2°C since the period 1861–1880, will require cumulative CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-emissions from all anthropogenic sources to stay between 0 and about 1000 Gt carbon since that period. [&amp;hellip;] An amount of 531 Gt carbon, was already emitted by 2011.&lt;/em&gt; One Gigatonne carbon (GtC) is equal to around 3.67 million tonnes CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-equivalent.
For more explanation on carbon budgets, see: &lt;a href="https://gofossilfree.org/understanding-the-carbon-budget/"&gt;https://gofossilfree.org/understanding-the-carbon-budget/&lt;/a&gt;.
The 2036-figure is based on: &lt;a href="https://www.carbonbrief.org/analysis-only-five-years-left-before-one-point-five-c-budget-is-blown"&gt;https://www.carbonbrief.org/analysis-only-five-years-left-before-one-point-five-c-budget-is-blown&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:carbonbudgets" title="Jump back to footnote 7 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:WEO2017"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This would lead to nearly a three-fold increase in solar and wind energy by 2040. This may sound impressive, until you realise that it would also lead to a significant growth in fossil fuel consumption.&lt;/em&gt;   &lt;br&gt;
These figures are based on table 2.2 of the &lt;a href="https://www.iea.org/reports/world-energy-outlook-2017"&gt;WEO-2017 report&lt;/a&gt;. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t explictly list wind and solar, but &amp;ldquo;other renewables&amp;rdquo; make up around 1.6% of global energy use in 2016, and would grow to around 4.4% in 2040 under the Current Policies scenario.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:WEO2017" title="Jump back to footnote 8 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="energy"></category><category term="energy"></category></entry></feed>